Thank you for joining us,
今月のプログラムにようこそ！
and welcome to the program!
It’s our privilege
to spend the next hour
愛する兄弟姉妹とご一緒でき
うれしく思います
with you dear brothers
and sisters.
Please join us
on a field trip to Ethiopia
エチオピアのステファノス・
デムサス兄弟をご紹介します
where we will meet
Brother Stephanos Demsas.
Brother Demsas and his wife
served faithfully for many years
デムサス兄弟姉妹は禁令下で
長年忠実に奉仕してこられました
while the preaching work
was under ban.
You will enjoy their experiences.
経験をお聞きしましょう
Have you ever participated
in a preaching campaign?
伝道キャンペーンに
参加したことがありますか？
Our team was present
when one was arranged in Armenia.
アルメニアのキャンペーン中に
カメラが入りました
A preaching campaign
is uplifting and encouraging
参加する皆が励みを受けたことが
分かるでしょう
to everyone involved
as this segment will show.
How would you react
if one of your loved ones decides
家族や友人が真理から離れたら
どう感じますか？
to leave the truth?
It truly is heartbreaking,
to say the least,
本当につらいことです
忍耐するのに役立つ
どんな聖書の原則があるでしょうか？
but what Bible principles
can help us endure
such a challenge?
ドラマから学びましょう
This dramatization will help us.
では 11月の
JW Broadcastingです！
This is the November program
of JW Broadcasting!
We have selected the theme
今月のテーマは—
“Be a Champion of Truth!”
“真理の擁護者になりましょう！”です
You may have heard
of the word “champion”
擁護者は 英語で
チャンピオンと言います
used in the context of sports.
What is a champion?
“チャンピオン”という言葉は
スポーツで聞いたことがおありでしょう
The word
can have different meanings.
チャンピオンとは何でしょうか？
The word is related
to the French word champ,
いろいろな意味があります
meaning “field.”
幾つかの言語で この言葉は
“野原”や“戦場”と関連しています
That word has its origin
in the Latin word campus,
also meaning “field”
or “battlefield.”
この意味合いは聖書中にも出てきます
The Bible speaks of
a champion on a battlefield
サムエル第一 17章4節に—
戦場でのチャンピオンついて
こう書かれています
in 1 Samuel 17:4:
“ときに ひとりの代表闘士
[英語でチャンピオン]が—”
“Then a champion came out
from the camps of the Philistines;
“フィリスティア人の陣営から
出て来たが—”
his name was Goliath.”
“その名をゴリアテといい……”
Goliath was a champion
for a wrong cause,
ゴリアテは 古代イスラエルを
打ち破るために—
namely,
to take the lead in defeating
戦いで先頭に立つという
誤った大義のチャンピオンー
the ancient Israelites in battle.
つまり擁護者でした
In our modern time,
according to one definition,
現代において 英語のチャンピオン
という言葉の一つの定義は—
a champion
is “an ardent defender
“ある大義や人の 熱心な
擁護者あるいは支持者”です
“or supporter of a cause
or another person.”
今日のクリスチャンは
真理の熱心な擁護者 また支持者です
Christians today
are ardent defenders
and supporters of the truth.
The Watchtower
of January 15, 2012,
「ものみの塔」誌2012年1月15日号
8ページにはこうあります
said on page 8:
“Other champions
“その後の数世紀には
次のような人たちが登場して—”
of Bible truth rose up
in the centuries that followed.”
“聖書の真理を擁護しました”
何十年も前
「ものみの塔」誌はこう述べました
Years before,
The Watchtower said:
“This magazine
will never shrink in fear
“本誌が恐れのためにしりごみし—”
from championing the truth!”
“真理を擁護しなくなるような
ことは決してありません！”
“The Watchtower
has been championing
“「ものみの塔」誌は『王国の真理という
大義』を擁護してきました”
‘the cause of Kingdom truth.’”
So, are you a champion?
では あなたはチャンピオン
つまり擁護者ですか？
In a sports competition,
スポーツ競技では
一人だけがチャンピオンになります
only one individual
gets to be the champion.
But in the case
of true Christians,
しかし 真のクリスチャンの場合
皆が真理のチャンピオンになれます
all can be champions
of the truth.
All Christians
are to defend the truth
つまり 皆が真理を擁護し
征服者また勝利者になるべきです
and become conquerors
—winners.
It’s necessary
to defend the truth
真理を擁護すべきなのは—
because in today’s world
真理が攻撃され
ねじ曲げられているからです
truth is being attacked
and distorted.
We are surrounded
by a sea of lies
今の世はうそと虚偽で
満ちあふれています
and misrepresentations.
How did such lies get started?
うそはどのように
始まったのでしょうか？
サタンがエデンの園で
エバにうそをついたのが始まりです
They started in the garden of Eden
when Satan told Eve lies.
Satan,
through his deceptive statements,
サタンは欺きの発言によって
“偽りの父”となりました
became “the father of the lie.”
All the problems in the world
この世のすべての問題
個人的なものも含め—
—all calamities
(also your personal calamities),
すべての災難 戦争 病気
犯罪 不幸 悲しみ 死は—
all wars,
all diseases, all crimes,
all unhappiness,
sorrow, and death
エデンの園の最初の
うそから始まったのです
—started with the original lies
in the garden of Eden.
Satan is “the father of the lie.”
サタンは“偽りの父”です
そして今では たくさんの
偽りの“子どもたち”がいます
But today there are
many “children” of the lie.
わたしたちはみな
その影響を受けています
Every one of us is affected.
We are surrounded
by a sea of lies.
うそに取り囲まれています
A lie is “a false statement
うそとは“誤った陳述を—”
“deliberately presented
as being true;
“意図的に正しいものとして
示すこと—”
a falsehood.”
“偽り”です
A lie is the opposite
of the truth.
うそは真実の反対です
Lying involves
saying something incorrect
うそには あることについて
真実を知る権利のある人に—
to a person who is entitled to know
the truth about a matter.
不正確なことを語ることが
関係しています
But there is also something
that is called a half-truth.
しかし いわゆる半分だけの
真実もあります
The Bible tells Christians
to be honest with each other.
聖書はクリスチャンが
互いに正直であるべきと述べています
“Now that you
have put away deceit,
“あなた方は偽りを
捨て去ったのですから—”
. . . speak truth,”
wrote the apostle Paul
“真実を語りなさい”とパウロは
エフェソス 4章25節で書いています
at Ephesians 4:25.
Lies and half-truths
undermine trust.
うそや半分だけの真実は
信頼を損ないます
A German proverb says,
“一度うそをつくと 本当のことを
言っても信じてもらえない”—
“Who lies once is not believed,
even if he says the truth.”
というドイツのことわざがあります
So we need to speak openly
それで 率直に正直に語り合うべきです
and honestly with each other,
not withholding
bits of information
ある情報を言わないことによって—
that could change
the perception of the listener
聞く人に誤解を与えるべきでは
ありません
or mislead him.
As to lies,
there are different types.
うそには様々な種類があります
Some politicians
have lied about matters
隠すためにうそをつく政治家がいます
they wanted to keep secret.
Companies sometimes lie
in advertisements
会社はうその製品宣伝をする
ことがあります
regarding their products.
ニュースメディアはどうでしょうか？
What about the news media?
Many try to report events truthfully.
多くは誠実に事件を
伝えようとしますが—
But we should not be gullible
新聞やラジオ テレビの言うこと
すべてをうのみにし—
and believe
everything newspapers write
or everything we hear on radio
何でもすぐに信じる人と
なるべきではありません
or see on television.
Then there are religious lies.
宗教上のうそもあります
If Satan is called
“the father of the lie,”
サタンが“偽りの父”ならば—
then Babylon the Great,
the global empire of false religion,
偽りの宗教の世界帝国
大いなるバビロンは—
can be called
the “mother” of the lie.
偽りの“母”と言えます
Individual false religions
個々の偽りの宗教は
偽りの“娘”と言えるでしょう
could be called
“daughters” of the lie.
Some lie by saying that sinners
ある宗教は—
罪人は地獄で永遠の責め苦に遭う
といって うそをつきます
will get tormented in hell forever.
Others lie by saying,
“一度の救いは永久の救い”
という うそもあります
“Once saved, always saved.”
Again, others lie
by saying that the earth
裁きの日に地球は燃え尽き—
will be burned up
on Judgment Day
善人はみな天に行く
という うそもあります
and all good people
will go to heaven.
Some worship idols.
偶像を崇拝する宗教もあります
Paul wrote at Romans 1:25:
パウロはローマ 1章25節で
こう書いています
“They exchanged
the truth of God for the lie
“すなわちそれは
神の真理を偽りと換え—”
“and venerated
and rendered sacred service
“創造した方より
創造物をあがめて—”
to the creation
rather than the Creator.”
“それに神聖な奉仕を
ささげた者たちです”
Then there are many lies
of a personal nature
人々が普段の生活でつく
個人的なうそもたくさんあります
that people express
in everyday life.
A businessman
may get a phone call
ビジネスマンは電話を受けた時—
不在だと答えるよう
秘書に言うことがあります
but tell his secretary
to answer the caller
それは小さなうそかもしれません
by saying he is not in.
This may be considered
a small lie.
うそには 小さなうそ—
There are small lies,
big lies,
大きなうそ—
悪意のあるうそがあります
and malicious lies.
子どもが何かを壊した時—
A child may have broken something
but when asked initially,
最初は罰が怖くて 壊していないと
言うことがあります
out of fear of punishment,
denies having done it.
でも 悪意のあるうそつきに
なるわけではありません
This does not make the child
a malicious liar.
In contrast,
what if an entrepreneur
対照的に 事業家が
税金をごまかすため—
tells his bookkeeper
to falsify the entries
経理に簿記の記載を偽るように
言う場合には どうでしょうか？
in the books
in order to save on taxes?
This lying to the tax office
税務署へのこのうそは重大です
is certainly a serious lie.
It is a deliberate attempt
to mislead somebody
これは知る権利のある人を
故意に欺くことです
that has the right to know.
定められた正当な収入を
政府から奪うことでもあります
It also robs the government
of what they have established
as legal income.
We can see
that not all lies are the same;
すべてのうそが同じでなく—
小さなうそ 大きなうそ
悪意のあるうそがあることが分かります
there are small lies, big lies,
and malicious lies.
Satan is a malicious liar.
サタンは悪意のあるうそつきで
うそのチャンピオンです
He is the champion of the lie.
エホバは偽り者を憎んでおられるので—
Since Jehovah hates liars,
大きなうそや悪意のあるうそだけでなく
すべてのうそを避けるべきです
we should avoid all lies,
not just big or malicious lies.
では 真理は見いだせるでしょうか？
But can we find the truth?
“真理は相対的である”
と言う人がいます
Some say, “Truth is relative.”
It is like saying,
“This is truth for you,
“あなたにとっての真理はこれで—”
“わたしにとっての真理は
これです”と言うのです
and this is truth for me.”
This claim is not logical
宗教的な真理では
これは論理的ではありません
when it comes to religious truth.
Either God is a Trinity
or he’s not.
神は三位一体か そうでないかの
どちらかです
Either the soul is mortal
or it is not.
魂は滅びるか 滅びないかの
どちらかです
Either there is a future paradise
on earth or there is not.
将来 地上の楽園があるか ないかの
どちらかです
Either homosexuality
is acceptable to God or it is not.
同性愛は神に受け入れられるか
そうでないかのどちらかです
Either participating in wars
is permissible or it is not.
戦争に参加できるか できないかの
どちらかです
真理は明確であり
相対的ではありません
Truth is definite, not relative,
because Jehovah conveyed
the truth to his servants.
エホバがご自分の僕に
真理を伝えられたからです
Psalm 43:3 says:
詩編 43編3節には—
“Send out your light and your truth.”
“あなたの光と真理とを
送り出してください”とあります
Jehovah is a Revealer of truth.
エホバが真理の啓示者なのです
One of several reasons
why Jesus came into the world
イエスがこの世に来た理由の一つは
“真理について証しする”ためです
was to “witness to the truth.”
At John 18:37b,
ヨハネ 18章37節後半で
イエスはこう言われました
he said:
“For this I have been born,
“真理について証しすること
このためにわたしは生まれ—”
“and for this
I have come into the world,
“that I should bear witness
to the truth.
“このためにわたしは世に来ました”
Everyone who is on the side
of the truth listens to my voice.”
“真理の側にいる者はみな
わたしの声を聴きます”
So if we listen to Jesus,
or read in the Bible
それで イエスの話されることを聞く—
つまり その教えを聖書から読むなら—
what he taught,
we can learn the truth.
真理を学べます
Jesus was the personification
of the truth.
イエスは真理を体現し—
“わたしは道であり 真理であり
命です”と言われました
He said: “I am the way
and the truth and the life.”
We can find out what the truth is
聖書を勤勉に研究するなら
真理とは何かが分かります
by diligently studying the Bible.
Truth is that which is a fact.
真理とは 事実のことです
For true Christians,
the entire text
真のクリスチャンにとって—
ヘブライ語聖書と
クリスチャン・ギリシャ語聖書全体は—
of the Hebrew
and Christian Greek Scriptures
真理です
constitutes the truth.
詩編 119編160節は
エホバについてこう述べています
Psalm 119:160
says of Jehovah:
‘The essence
of your word is truth.’
“あなたのみ言葉の本質は真理です”
That is why
it is good to do
ですから 深く考えながら
聖書を毎日読み—
daily Bible reading
with meditation
家族の崇拝を毎週
行なうのは良いことです
and weekly family worship.
At Matthew 24:45-47, we read
マタイ 24章45-47節によると
イエスは終わりの日に—
that for the time of the end,
Jesus would appoint
“忠実で思慮深い奴隷”
つまり統治体を任命して—
a “faithful and discreet slave,”
or Governing Body,
ご自分の追随者に聖書を説明し—
to explain the Bible
to His followers
and help them to grow
in understanding of the truth.
真理を一層理解できるようにされます
Whereas Jesus’ teachings
イエスの教えと書き記された
神の言葉は霊感を受けています
and the written Word of God
are inspired,
“the faithful and discreet slave”
is not inspired,
“忠実で思慮深い奴隷”は
真理を擁護するものの—
although it champions the truth.
霊感を受けてはいません
しかし 忠実な奴隷は
霊的食物を供給します
Nevertheless, the faithful slave
provides spiritual food.
Whereas in the first century
1世紀に 使徒や聖書筆者たちは—
there was supernatural knowledge
超自然の知識を用いる
ことができましたが—
available for apostles
and Bible writers,
コリント第一 13章8節に
示されているように—
in the time of the end,
Jehovah does not bestow
this miraculous gift anymore,
as explained
終わりの日には エホバはもはやこの
奇跡的な賜物を与えてはおられません
at 1 Corinthians 13:8.
Although there is
no divine inspiration today,
今日 神の霊感はないとしても—
イエスは忠実な奴隷の働きを通して
民を漸進的に導いておられます
still Jesus leads
his people progressively
through the services
of the faithful slave.
イエスは 不完全な忠実な奴隷が—
Jesus trusts
that the imperfect faithful slave
最善を尽くして霊的食物を供給すると
信頼しておられるのです
will do its best
to convey spiritual food.
Do you also trust the slave?
あなたも奴隷を信頼していますか？
Whereas the truth
of God’s Word does not change,
神の言葉の真理は変わりませんが
わたしたちの理解は変化します
our understanding
of the truth does change
わたしたちはまだ完全でないからです
because we
are not perfect yet.
We understand more
about the truth today
1世紀のクリスチャンより 今のほうが
よりよく真理を理解しています
than Christians
in the first century.
真理の漸進的な理解に
ついていっているでしょうか？
Do we keep up with the progressive
understanding of truth?
ダニエルはこう告げられました
Daniel was told:
“Many will rove about,
“多くの者が行き巡り
真の知識が満ちあふれる”
and the true knowledge
will become abundant.”
この過程は 徐々に進みます
This is a gradual process.
わたしたちはまだ行き巡っています
We are still roving about.
During the Millennium,
Jehovah will reveal
千年統治の間 エホバは人類に
付加的な真理を啓示されます
additional truths to mankind.
At Revelation 20:12,
啓示 20章12節は 開かれる
数々の巻き物について言及しています
it mentions scrolls
that will be opened.
使徒ヨハネは “死んだ者たちはそれらの
巻き物に書かれている事柄により—”
The apostle John reports
that the dead are to be “judged
“out of those things
written in the scrolls
“その行ないにしたがって
裁かれる”と述べました
according to their deeds.”
Evidently, then,
these scrolls will contain
ですから これらの巻き物は—
千年期の人類のための
付加的な情報を含んでいます
additional information for mankind
during the thousand years.
It stands to reason
that after the end of the Millennium,
千年期の後にも—
学ぶべき付加的な真理があると
考えるのは 道理にかなったことです
there will be
additional truths to learn.
Still,
according to Ecclesiastes
それでも 伝道の書 3章11節
にはこうあります
chapter 3, verse 11:
“まことの神の行なわれた業を—”
“Mankind will never find out
“人間が決して見いだすことが
できないようにされた”
the work
that the true God has made.”
But how do we know
we have the truth?
では わたしたちが真理を持っていると
なぜ分かるのでしょうか？
At Pentecost 33
of our Common Era,
西暦33年 ペンテコステの際—
true Christians
numbered only about 3,000.
真のクリスチャンは
たった3千人ほどでした
Today, we are millions.
今日 わたしたちは数百万人です
And on average,
every weekend
毎週末に平均5千人以上が
バプテスマを受けています
more than 5,000
are getting baptized.
But this in itself
しかし それ自体は
証拠ではありません
is not proof
that we have the truth.
数では測れないからです
Truth is not measured
in numbers.
真理を持っていると
なぜ分かるのでしょうか？
Why do we know
we have the truth?
For one,
because we remain
一つ目に イエスの教えのうちに
とどまっているからです
in Jesus’ teaching,
John 8:31.
ヨハネ 8章31節
Second,
we know we have the truth
二番目に 互いに優しい愛情の
深いきずながあるからです
because of the deep bond of love
for each other, John 13:35.
ヨハネ 13章35節
Third, we know we have the truth
because our conduct
三番目に 真理の高い道徳基準に
固く従っているからです
adheres
to the high moral standards of truth,
ヨハネ 15章10節
John 15:10.
Fourth,
we know we have the truth
四番目に ヨハネ 17章14節の
イエスの忠告にそって—
because we remain neutral
in the controversies of the world,
この世の論争において
中立を保っているからです
as Jesus advised
at John 17:14.
五番目に 神の名を担う民だからです
Fifth,
we know we have the truth
because we are
God’s name people.
使徒 15章14節は—
Acts 15:14 speaks
“ご自分のみ名のための民”
について述べています
of “a people for his name.”
Jesus said:
“The truth will set you free.”
イエスは “真理はあなた方を
自由にするでしょう”と言われました
It sets us free from fears
—like the fear of death,
死への恐れ 将来の恐れ
人への過度の恐れから自由になります
fear of the future,
and an exaggerated fear of man.
It also sets us free
from false teachings,
偽りの教え 心霊術 占星術
魔術から自由になります
from spiritism,
and from astrology and magic.
不道徳とその結果から自由になります
It frees us from immorality
and its consequences.
わたしたちほど 霊的に自由な民は
この地上に存在しません
There are
no other people on earth
that are
as spiritually free as we are.
その自由に感謝していますか？
Do we appreciate that freedom?
真理は自由をもたらします
Truth leads to freedom.
コリント第二 3章17節は—
Second Corinthians 3:17 says:
“エホバの霊のある所には
自由があります”と述べています
“Where the spirit of Jehovah is,
there is freedom.”
The truth penetrates schools.
How so?
真理は学校に達しています
どのようにでしょうか？
By means of our children
who preach the truth
子どもたちがクラスメートや先生に
真理を伝えることによってです
to classmates and to teachers.
Do you go to school?
あなたは学校に通っていますか？
Do you champion
the truth at school?
学校で真理を擁護していますか？
How can you do this?
どうすればよいでしょうか？
You do this not only by preaching
but also by your conduct,
証言だけでなく 行動や服装で—
by your dress and grooming,
また クリスチャンに
ふさわしくない活動に参加せず—
and by taking a stand for the truth
when others want you
真理に堅く立つことによってです
to participate
in unchristian practices.
さらに いつも正直で
カンニングしないことによっても—
You also champion the truth
by remaining honest
and not cheating
on your exams.
真理を擁護できます
エホバはそうする皆さんを愛されます
And Jehovah
will love you for that.
The truth
also penetrates prisons.
真理は刑務所にも達しています
Reports have come in
from many countries
さまざまな刑務所で囚人に会い—
telling of the good work
brothers are doing
霊的援助を行なう
兄弟たちの良い働きについて—
in contacting prisoners
in various prisons,
多くの国から報告が寄せられています
helping some to rehabilitate
their lives spiritually.
In a number of such institutions,
そのような施設の多くで
集会が定期的に開かれ—
regular meetings are being held
and several prisoners
have studied to the point
献身とバプテスマに
至った囚人もいます
of dedication and baptism.
The truth penetrates
even walls of monasteries.
真理は修道院の壁さえも
突き破っています
In Mexico, in 2009,
メキシコで2009年 一人の修道女が
バプテスマを受けました
a nun was baptized who,
because of the truth,
彼女は女子修道院長でしたが—
had left
her monastery and order,
真理のために修道院と
修道会を去りました
although she was
the mother superior.
The world
is in utter confusion.
この世はまったく混乱しています
What a blessing
to know the truth!
真理を知るのは 何と大きな祝福
喜びなのでしょう！
We rejoice in it!
We have the truth on our lips.
唇に真理があり
腰に真理を帯びています
We have the truth around our hips.
Ephesians chapter 6
says that “the belt of truth”
エフェソス 6章が述べるように
“真理の帯”を腰に固く締めます
is fastened around our waists.
We are ready to teach it.
真理を喜んで教え 真理を語り
真理のうちを歩みます
We talk the truth,
and we walk in the truth.
真理のうちを歩み続ける人は
永遠にその道を歩みます
Those who continue to walk
in the truth
will walk in it forever.
Help your students
to love the truth
研究生が真理を愛し 真理に生き—
and to live the truth but,
if necessary,
必要とあれば 真理とエホバのために—
to be willing to die
for the truth and for Jehovah.
死をも辞さない決意を
持つよう助けましょう
The truth is invincible
真理は無敵であり
この邪悪な世を征服します
and will conquer
this wicked world.
In some countries,
we may have many enemies
ある国では わたしたちを
沈黙させようとする敵が多くいます
who may want to silence us.
But the apostle Paul said
しかし 使徒パウロは—
at 2 Corinthians 13:8:
コリント第二 13章8節で
こう言っています
“わたしたちは真理に逆らっては
何も行なえません”
“For we can do nothing
against the truth.”
Neither can our enemies
suppress the truth.
敵も真理を押さえつける
ことはできません
唯一の真理を持っていることに
感謝していますか？
Do we appreciate
that we have the truth
—the only truth?
Is this arrogant to say?
By no means!
そう言うのは高慢でしょうか？
いいえ そう言わないなら
罪になるでしょう
It would be a sin
if we would not say so.
イエスは謙遜でしたが
“わたしは真理です”と言われました
Jesus was not arrogant
when he said:
‘I am the truth.’
To know the truth
is not enough.
真理を知るだけでなく
擁護すべきです
We need to champion it.
真理を愛する人は
まだたくさんいます
There are still
many lovers of truth out there;
探しましょう！
search for them.
誰の助けがあるでしょうか？
Who will help you
in the search?
イエスはヨハネ 4章23節で—
According to John 4:23,
エホバが 真理をもって崇拝することを
願う人を探しておられると述べました
Jesus said that Jehovah
is searching for ones
that want to worship in truth.
大多数は“光よりむしろ
闇を愛し”ており耳を傾けません
The majority
will not listen to the truth
because ‘they love the darkness
rather than the light.’
真理により自分の罪深い行ないが
あらわにされたとき—
The truth may expose
their sinful conduct,
悔い改めて変化する
謙遜さがないのかもしれません
and they
may not have the humility
to want
to repent and change.
それでも 宣べ伝え警告すべきです！
We still have to preach to them
—to warn them.
神はエゼキエルにこう言われました
Ezekiel was told:
“あなたは わたしから彼らに
警告しなければならない”
“You must warn them from me.”
The principle applies to us as well.
この原則はわたしたちにも
当てはまります
Paul speaks of “the sword
of . . . God’s word.”
パウロは“剣 すなわち神の言葉”
に言及しました
Use it well
to champion the truth.
真理を擁護するためにチャンピオンとして
それを上手に使いましょう
Train your students
to be good defenders of it as well.
真理の優れた擁護者となるよう
研究生も訓練しましょう
The time will come
in Paradise after the final test
最後の試みの後—
when it will not be necessary
楽園では 真理を擁護する
必要はなくなります
to champion,
or defend, the truth,
もはやだれも真理を攻撃しないからです
because nobody
will attack it anymore.
Right now,
whether we are adults,
今は 大人も 若者も 子どもも—
teenagers, or children,
let us follow and imitate Jesus
真理の最大の擁護者である
イエスに従い 倣いましょう！
—the greatest Champion of truth!
そのために 真理を学び続け
広く伝え続けましょう
To that end,
keep studying the truth.
Keep spreading the truth.
真理と 真理の神エホバを
愛し続けましょう
Keep loving the truth
and Jehovah, the God of truth.
Hold fast to the truth
as to a lifeline
命綱である真理を
しっかりつかむのです
—as this is what it is!
忠実を保つなら
ハルマゲドンを生き残るとしても—
By staying faithful,
whether you survive Armageddon
楽園で復活するとしても—
or are resurrected in Paradise,
勝利を収めた真理の擁護者に
なれるでしょう！
you will be a victorious
champion of the truth!
Let’s now look at some examples
of how our brothers and sisters
では 世界の兄弟姉妹が—
どのように忠実に真理を
擁護しているか見てみましょう
around the world
faithfully champion the truth.
Chris?
クリス
Thank you, Brother Lösch.
レッシュ兄弟 ありがとうございます
When a dear friend or perhaps
親しい友人や家族が真理から離れるなら
とても厳しい試練となりえます
even a family member leaves the truth,
it can be a very challenging situation.
It can truly be a test of our faith
信仰が本当に試されます
when we see something
like that take place.
次のドラマを見ながら
エホバに忠節を保つことによって—
While watching
this dramatization,
pay attention to how the mother
was able to champion the truth
母親がどのように真理を擁護する
ことができたかに注目してください
by remaining
loyal to Jehovah.
ガブリエラです
My name is Gabriella.
Ben and I have always enjoyed
夫のベンとわたしは
ずっと集会を楽しんできたのですが—
attending the meetings.
But lately,
最近は—
it’s been difficult.
たいへんです
Something was missing
大切なものを失いました
—our son.
息子です
It was like watching a movie
of someone else’s family.
夢なら覚めてほしいと思いました
I couldn’t believe
this was happening to us.
こんなことがわたしたちに起きるなんて...
Our son, Levi,
息子のリーバイは—
was no longer
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
もうエホバの証人ではないのです
The elders and friends
in the congregation
長老や友人たちは
本当に優しく支えてくれました
were so supportive
and understanding.
みんな リーバイの成長を
見守ってくれていた人たちなんです
Many of them
watched Levi grow up,
give his first talk,
初めての割り当ての時も
バプテスマを受けた時も
get baptized.
I was so torn.
取り乱していました
I was disappointed in Levi
for leaving Jehovah,
リーバイが
エホバを捨てたこともそうですが—
but I was
more disappointed in myself.
それ以上にがっかりしたのは
自分に対してです
I felt like we
failed him somehow.
親として失格だと感じました
I kept wondering
how he was doing.
息子のことが頭から離れませんでした
Was he OK?
どうしているのかと…
Then, as hard
as the past few weeks had been,
そして—
ただでさえつらい気持ちが
耐えがたいものになりました
it just got harder.
I knew what the Bible said
クリスチャンの歩みを捨てる
どんな者との“交友”も—
about “quit mixing in company
with anyone”
やめなければならないことは
わかっていました
who is not living
according to Christian standards.
でも 自分が
そうしなければならないなんて…
But I never thought that scripture
would one day apply to me.
Later that evening,
a brother was talking
その日の晩
コラの子たちについての話がありました
about the example
of Korah’s sons.
Jehovah confirmed that He
was using Moses
エホバはモーセを用いていることを
明らかにされました
to lead His people,
not Korah.
コラではありません
エホバが反逆者たちの天幕から
離れるようにと人々に告げた時—
When the people were told
to move away
from the rebels’ tents,
what would Korah’s sons do?
コラの子たちは—
Would they put loyalty to family
ahead of loyalty to Jehovah?
家族よりもエホバに
忠節を示すかどうかが試されました
The Bible tells us
that his sons remained loyal
彼らはエホバへの忠節を保ち—
to Jehovah
and were blessed for it.
祝福されました
That night,
after the meeting,
その晩 息子からのメールについて
夫に話しました
I told Ben about the text
I received from Levi.
I told him everything
気持ちも全部 話しました
—how I missed Levi so much,
どれほど 息子を思っているか—
でも エホバに忠節でありたい
but that I also wanted to be loyal
to Jehovah like Korah’s sons.
コラの子たちのように…
Ben admitted that he too
夫も 自分のつらい気持ちを
話してくれました
had been struggling
with feelings like mine.
でも 夫の話にはっとさせられました
But then he said something
that I hadn’t thought of.
If we were to stand between Levi
僕たちが リーバイとエホバの間に
立って—
and the discipline he needs,
懲らしめに手心を加るなら—
we would, in effect,
be blocking
実際には—
エホバの愛がリーバイに届くのを
妨げることになる
an expression of Jehovah’s love
from reaching him.
In fact,
it’s our very loyalty
だから—
僕たちがエホバに忠実でないといけない
to Jehovah
that could save his life.
息子を救えるのはエホバなんだから と
We agreed to continue
to put our trust
エホバを信頼し忠節を保てるように
二人で祈りました
in Jehovah
and stay loyal to him.
It’s been five years now,
あれから５年になります
and while Levi
still hasn’t returned to Jehovah,
まだ 息子は戻ってきていません
でも あきらめません
I haven’t given up hope on him.
息子が戻るその日まで
開拓者として一生懸命に働きます
Until that day,
I’m staying busy as a regular pioneer
and focusing my energies
エホバを知ることができるよう
他の人のために… 一心に
on helping others
learn about Jehovah.
I’ve come to experience firsthand
詩編 97編10節の言葉を実感しました
the truth of Psalm 97:10.
エホバは 本当に
忠節な者たちを守られます
Jehovah really does guard
his loyal ones.
What helped Gabriella overcome
this difficult challenge?
ガブリエラが
厳しい試練を乗り越えるのに—
何が助けになったでしょうか？
For example,
when she received
a text message from her son,
たとえば 息子からメールが来た時—
she applied Scriptural counsel
聖句の助言を
自分の状況に当てはめました
to her personal circumstances.
The good example of Korah’s sons
コラの息子たちの
良い模範からも力を得—
gave her added motivation
so as not to allow
息子への感情に
流されたりしませんでした
her feelings for her son
to dictate her actions.
Instead, she was firm
in her loyalty to Jehovah.
エホバに忠節をしっかりと示しました
Also, her husband, Ben,
had found an article
夫のベンも役立つ記事を見つけ
自分たちがエホバと息子との間に—
that helped
the two of them appreciate
that they should make sure
not to stand
立ちはだからないことの
大切さを理解しました
between Jehovah
and their son, Levi.
Instead, they wanted
Jehovah’s expression of love
そして エホバの愛の表明が
リーバイに届くことを望みました
to reach Levi.
Whenever we
are faced with a trial,
わたしたちも
試練に面した時はいつでも—
we need to remember
to pray constantly
エホバに導きをたゆまず祈り求め—
to Jehovah for guidance
and to look for Jehovah’s counsel
出版物や集会で
エホバの助言を探すべきです
in our literature
and during our meetings.
The apostle Paul faced
many challenges in his ministry.
使徒パウロは宣教で
たくさんの試練に直面しました
In 2 Corinthians chapter 11,
starting in verse 23,
コリント第二 11章23節以降—
パウロは宣教で経験した
20以上の困難を列挙しています
he enumerates
over 20 hardships
that he experienced
in his ministry.
What helped Paul
to keep his motivation strong
これらすべてに直面しても
なぜ意欲を強く保てたのでしょうか？
despite everything he faced?
In this morning worship
from Bethel,
ベテルの朝の崇拝で
ジョン・エクラン兄弟が—
Brother John Ekrann highlights
パウロ自身の言葉から説明しています
what Paul himself said
kept him going.
When you look
at the words in the way
パウロが用いた 次の表現から
何が分かるでしょうか？
that the apostle Paul worded things,
こう述べています
he said: “I live by faith
in the Son of God,
“わたしは神のみ子に対する
信仰によって生きているのです”
who loved me
and handed himself over for me.”
“み子はわたしを愛し わたしのために
ご自身を渡してくださったのです”
And we can really see
the very personal nature
パウロは贖いを
個人的なものとみなしました
of the ransom to the apostle Paul.
And it’s important for us to do
これはわたしたちにとっても
重要なことです
—as our commenters
pointed out nicely—
it is important for us
to personalize the ransom.
贖いを自分個人に対するものと
みなすのです
The apostle Paul, in Hebrews 6:5,
パウロは
ヘブライ 6章5節で—
showed the very personal nature;
聖書や贖いを
個人的にとらえるという点を—
he understood the personal nature
次のような表現で
表わしています
of the Bible and the ransom.
In Hebrews 6:5,
ヘブライ 6章5節です
he uses this expression:
“神の優れた言葉と
来たるべき事物の体制の力とを—”
“And who have tasted
the fine word of God
“味わっておきながら”
and powers
of the coming system of things.”
Well, it’s interesting
he used the word “taste.”
“味わう”とは
極めて 個人的なことで—
Taste is something very personal.
誰かに代わってしてもらう
ことはできません
Somebody can’t taste
something for you.
自分の口に入れなければ
実際の味はわかりません
You have to put it
in your mouth in order
to really know
what it’s going to taste like.
So, too, with the ransom.
贖いも同じです
And what practical ways
can we “taste,”
では どうすれば 贖いを”味わう” —
つまり 個人的にとらえる
ことができるでしょうか？
or personalize,
the ransom for us?
Let’s just consider
a couple this morning.
二つの点を考えましょう
One is personal fears.
一つ目は 自分は神から愛されて
いるだろうか？
‘Does God really love me?
それに値するだろうか？
という不安です
Am I worthy of love?’
Sometimes the “what-ifs”
and their cousins, the “could-bes,”
時折 わたしたちは—
まだ生じてもいないことで
煩うことがあります
they come to live and never leave.
そして 実際に試練や困難が生じると—
You know, if bad things
or trials or difficulties happen to us,
”エホバはわたしを愛して
おられないのかもしれない”—
we begin to reason,
‘Well, Jehovah God maybe doesn’t love me.’
と考えるのです
There’s really strong reason for us
わたしたちは 何にでも
原因と結果があると考えがちです
to somehow believe
in cause and effect.
We see the cause of things and effect,
and so after a while,
その視点が定着すると—
自分に生じることには すべて
原因があると考えるようになり—
everything that happens to us,
we begin to look at some cause
and even begin to think
that maybe Jehovah
エホバに愛されていないからだとまで
考えてしまうかもしれません
doesn’t love us.
Even if we’re a good person
良いことを行なっているのに
悪いことが生じると—
and bad things happen to us,
we begin to wonder,
“同年代の人は みんな健康なのに
なぜ？” と考えたり—
‘Others my age are healthy.’
Some leaving
or changing assignments,
新たな割り当てを受けて
ここを去っていく人について—
you hear everything
falls into place
あっという間に
物事が決まったと聞くと—
for them within a few weeks.
‘I’m still looking for a job.
I’m still looking for work.’
“わたしはまだ
仕事も決まっていないのに...”—
と考えたりします
In other words,
do not try to reason
しかし 物事が思い通りに
ならないからといって—
that just because things
don’t work out perfectly
エホバから愛されていない
というわけでは決してありません
that Jehovah doesn’t love us.
It’s not true.
We can still be doing very,
very good things,
どんなに良いことを行なっていても
困難に直面することがあります
and yet some difficulties
can face us.
For example,
you’re driving down the road,
たとえば 交通ルールを守って
運転をしていて—
obeying all the traffic laws.
You pull up to a red light,
you stop,
赤信号で止まり 青信号で
再び走り始めると—
it turns green, you go through it,
and you get broadsided
いきなり赤信号を無視してきた車に
衝突されるかもしれません
by some knucklehead who went
through the red light on the other side.
Well, that’s not your fault.
あなたのせいではありません
Are you going to say:
“Well, you know what?
そんなとき
”もう交通ルールなんて守らない—”
I’m not going to obey traffic laws anymore.
See, it doesn’t pay!”
“そんなの無駄だ”
などと言うでしょうか？
Well, no!
It was his fault for running
through the traffic light.
落ち度は 信号を
無視した方にあります
悪いことや困難は誰にでも生じえます
And sometimes bad, or difficult,
things can happen to us.
自分に落ち度があるのでも
神に愛されていないのでもありません
It’s not our fault
or it’s not any sign
that Jehovah doesn’t love us.
So how can reflecting
on the ransom help us
贖いについて黙想することは—
こうした不安に対処する
助けとなります
when we have these kinds
of personal fears?
Well, we could start with,
Why do we have the ransom?
贖いは なぜ備えられたのでしょうか？
Well, because some very bad things
それは 非常に好ましくないことが—
were happening
to some good people
アダムとエバの子孫である
わたしたちに及んだからです
—us—
Adam and Eve’s descendants.
I mean,
Adam sinned and Eve sinned,
二人が犯した罪の結果として
わたしたちは苦しんでいます
yet we suffer.
The ransom is Jehovah’s solution
贖いは
エホバがもたらす解決策です
for those who appreciate it.
この備えにより 神は
“その苦しみは知っている—”
It’s his way of telling us,
‘I know bad things are happening,
“でもわたしが解決する”
と言っておられるのです
and I’m working to fix it.’
Yes, when we reflect
on the reason
そうです エホバが贖いを
備えた理由を熟考すれば—
why Jehovah God
gave us the ransom,
it helps us to know
that Jehovah knows we suffer
わたしたちが ガンや高齢や
不完全さに苦しんでいることを—
from cancer and old age
and the sins and mistakes of others
神がご存じだということを
思い起こせます
and even our own imperfections.
See, tasting of the ransom in this way
そのように 贖いを
個人的に味わうなら—
means we’ll not get the feeling
試練に遭っても “エホバから愛されていない”
とは考えないでしょう
that Jehovah doesn’t love us
when trials befall us.
To the contrary, the ransom
むしろ贖いには
エホバとイエスの愛が—
is the greatest expression
of Jehovah’s and Jesus’ love for us
そして 諸問題を解決したいという
お二方の願いが表われています
and their desire to fix
the current mess we live in now.
How about,
let’s consider a second way
贖いを味わえる
二つ目の例は何でしょうか？
that we could reflect
on the ransom,
and that is the death
of someone close to us.
それは 近しい人の死です
Anyone who’s had someone
very close to them die
親しい人を亡くした
経験のある人ならだれでも—
knows the very helpless feeling
that you have,
自分には何もできず 無力に感じたことを
覚えているのではないでしょうか？
knowing that there’s
really nothing you can do.
In that instant when they die,
your hope
そして 贖いに基づく
復活の希望への期待や信仰は—
—your faith in the resurrection
based on the ransom—
かつてないほど現実的なものと
なったことでしょう
becomes more real to you
than any time in your entire life.
使徒 17章31節を見ると
使徒パウロは その講話の中で—
In Acts 17:31,
in a beautiful speech
that the apostle Paul gave,
he highlights
イエスの死と復活 そして贖いが—
that Jesus’ death
わたしたちのための
保証であるという点を強調しています
and resurrection and the ransom
was really a guarantee
that we have.
Here in Acts 17:31,
使徒 17章31節にこうあります
he says: “Because he has set a day
on which he purposes
“なぜなら ご自分が任命した
ひとりの人によって—”
“to judge the inhabited earth
in righteousness
“人の住む地を義をもって
裁くために日を定め—”
“by a man
whom he has appointed,
“彼を死人の中から復活させて—”
“and he has provided
a guarantee
“すべての人に保証を
お与えになったからです”
“to all men
by resurrecting him
from the dead.”
贖いと 贖いにより可能になった
すべてのことを個人として味わうなら—
So personalizing the ransom
and all that it makes possible
helps us to know that the resurrection is,
not just possible,
復活が起きるということだけでなく—
エホバとイエスが
わたしたちの父や母を—
but that Jehovah
and Jesus want to resurrect
愛する夫や妻を復活させたいと
願っておられることを感じ取れます
our mother, our father,
our beloved husband or a wife.
They care about each person
お二人は これまで生存した
個々の人を気遣い 熟知しています
that has ever lived or died
and know them
so intimately and so completely
ですから 各々を その記憶や
持っていた特質と共に—
that they can resurrect them completely
with all their memories
復活させることができるのです
and personality completely
as we knew them.
神がわたしたち個人を
愛しておられることの—
I mean, how much more personal
この上ない 証拠ではないでしょうか？
could God’s love for us
become than that?
You know, to bring our loved ones
back from the dead
死んだ人を
よみがえらせることは—
エホバが人類すべてと
わたしたち一人ひとりに—
is the ultimate statement
of Jehovah’s personal interest
個人的な関心を持っておられることの
究極の表われなのです
in each and every human being.
We are not just collateral damage
わたしたちは
エホバに対するサタンの戦いの—
in Satan’s war on Jehovah.
単なる犠牲者ではありません
The ransom is the way
贖いによってエホバは—
アダムとエバの死以降
サタンが引き起こしてきた—
that Jehovah plans
to undo all the harm
that Satan has caused
あらゆる害悪を
無に帰せしめてくださるのです
since the death of Adam and Eve.
実際 エホバは復活により—
In fact, the resurrection
is really Jehovah’s way
サタンの嘘が 全くの偽りであった
ことを証明されます
of proving all of Satan’s lies
completely false.
今日 サタンは人の死後に生じることについて
あらゆる偽りを広めています
When you think about it today,
Satan can perpetrate
all kinds of lies about what happens
to people after they die.
“ここにいる あそこに行く
来世がある 天国がある—”
‘They’re going to go here,
they’re going to go there,
‘they’re going to go to some afterlife,
they’re going to go to some paradise,
“動物になって帰ってくる”
という具合です
they’re going to come back
as some animal.’
But in the new world,
しかし 新しい世で人類の大多数が
復活してくるとき—
when the vast majority of people
have been resurrected,
そうした嘘は だれも欺くことが
できなくなるでしょう
that lie isn’t going
to be sold anymore.
Each one can tell everyone
死後には何もなく—
死後の世界などなかったことが
誰の目にも明らかになります
what happened to them
when they died
—nothing,
no afterlife.
どこかで生きていたわけでは無いのです
Everyone will know
that it’s nonexistence.
嘘は もう通用しません
エホバは わたしたちが愛する人の
死に直面すると—
That lie won’t work.
See, Jehovah knew
深い悲しみを抱くことをご存じです
that we would hurt terribly
それで贖いを備えられました
at the death of loved ones,
so he gave us the ransom
それにより “あなたの悲しみは
よくわかっている—”
as his way of telling us,
‘I know it hurts,
but please know
“でも わたしは最善の解決策を
持っている”—
that I have
the perfect solution in mind.’
と語っておられるのです
Now, we’ve just considered two ways
贖いについて黙想できる
二つの例を取り上げました
to reflect and meditate on the ransom,
パウロと同様 個人として
贖いを味わいましょう
like the apostle Paul did,
to really personalize it.
We just talked about personal fears
個人的に抱える不安と
愛する人の死について考慮しました
and the resurrection,
the death of someone close to us.
ぜひ 贖いについて黙想することから
他にもどんな益が得られるのか—
Imagine how many more ways
we can benefit today
そして それが自分個人にどんな影響を
与えるのかを考えていきましょう
from meditating on the ransom
and how it affects us personally.
As ministers of Jehovah,
わたしたちはエホバの奉仕者として
良い知らせを伝えています
we take part in preaching
the good news.
That good news includes
the wonderful provision
それには エクラン兄弟が
強調してくださった—
of the ransom
Brother Ekrann highlighted.
贖いの素晴らしい備えが含まれます
Have you ever participated
in a preaching campaign?
伝道キャンペーンに
参加したことがありますか？
I’m sure you
have enjoyed campaigns
きっと 記念式や地区大会への
招待キャンペーンを—
such as inviting
our neighbors to the Memorial
楽しまれたことでしょう
or the regional convention.
On occasion,
other campaigns are approved
時々 ある場所や言語グループで
特定の必要があり—
by the Service Committee
of the Governing Body
統治体の奉仕委員会が
キャンペーンを承認することがあります
when there is a specific need
in an area or language group.
We bring you a report
アルメニアの
特別キャンペーンについてご報告します
on a special campaign
in Armenia.
Armenia is an ancient country
with rich history,
アルメニアは長い歴史のある国で—
アララト山のそびえる
山岳地帯に位置しています
situated in the lands
of Mount Ararat.
In the Caucasus region,
Lake Sevan
セバン湖はカフカス地方の宝石と
たたえられています
is considered to be
a prized jewel.
Diversity of its flora and fauna
地方に行くと 動植物の美しさと
種類の多さに驚かされます
contribute to the unique
and beautiful countryside.
Yerevan, the capital,
首都エレバンは近代的かつ絵のように
美しい都市です
is a modern metropolis
with picturesque views
that remind many of Paris
with its trees, cafés,
エレバンの街路樹 カフェ 噴水などは
フランスのパリを思わせます
and beautiful water fountains.
Recently, a special three-week
preaching campaign took place.
先日 3週間の
特別な伝道キャンペーンが行われました
Groups of Armenian-speaking
Jehovah’s Witnesses
6か国に住む
アルメニア語を話すエホバの証人が—
from six different countries
このキャンペーンへの招待に応じました
wholeheartedly responded
to the invitation.
The main purpose of the campaign
was to cover as many
キャンペーンの目標は—
この国の512の未割り当て区域を
できる限り網羅することでした
of the 512 unassigned territories
as possible
with the Kingdom good news.
Thus, an opportunity
さらに 地元の証人たちと
海外からの参加者たちが—
for an interchange
of encouragement was created
励まし合う機会を
作ることにもなりました
for both the local friends
and the campaign participants.
参加者たちは空港で
地元の兄弟姉妹から歓迎されました
They were warmly greeted
at the airport
by local brothers and sisters.
The Witnesses made good use
of their tablets and smartphones to show
証人たちは
タブレットやスマホを使って—
jw.orgからビデオを見せました
videos from the jw.org website.
Armenia is also currently home
アルメニアには現在—
1万1千人以上の
西アルメニア人難民がいます
to over 11,000 Western-Armenian refugees.
A special effort was made
to share with these individuals
母語の西アルメニア語で
聖書からの希望と—
the positive message of hope
and peace from the Bible
平和のメッセージを伝えるための
努力も払われました
in their native tongue,
West Armenian.
Metropolitan witnessing
served as an effective way
大都市での証言はその点
とても効果的でした
to reach these ones.
It was the first time in my life
初めて公の証言に参加しましたが
とても励みになりました
that I participated in public witnessing,
and it was very encouraging.
興味を示して近づいて来た人に
その人の母語で証言できました
When individuals would approach us
and show interest,
I could explain to them
the truth in their own language.
すごく良かったです
It was amazing.
It’s been very heartwarming.
区域の反応がすごく良くて
嬉しくなりました
People have really responded well.
皆さん良い知らせを欲しておられます
They were in need of comfort
and the good news, especially those that
西アルメニアの方たちは 特にそうです
we came for,
the Western Armenians.
ほとんどすべてのお宅で
中に入れて下さり—
Pretty much every door invited us in,
and they were very hospitable
and receptive.
よく聞いてくださいました
After we heard the announcement
about the special campaign
アルメニアで西アルメニア語での
特別キャンペーンが行われると聞いて—
in the Western language
that’s going to take place in Armenia,
“絶対参加しなきゃ”と思いました
we said: “We cannot miss this.
“We have to be there
and bring our share
こんなに喜びの多いキャンペーンを
逃したくはありませんでした
in this very joyful
preaching campaign.”
During the three-week campaign,
3週間で1万5千以上の出版物が
関心ある人に手渡され—
over 15,000 pieces
of Bible-based literature
were left with interested ones,
200件を超える研究が
取り決められました
and over 200 Bible studies
were started.
We were very happy to see
キャンペーンのために—
how many brothers and sisters
were ready to come
大勢の兄弟姉妹が
世界各地から来てくださったので—
for the campaign in Armenia
とても励まされました
from different countries
around the world.
That response showed
それを見て エホバの祝福を
確信しました
that Jehovah has blessed our efforts.
Those who came from far and wide
世界各地から参加した兄弟姉妹も
大きな喜びを味わいました
greatly appreciated the share
they had in this special event.
Everyone was so happy to see us.
お会いした皆さんに
聖書を差し上げました
And when we were giving them a Bible,
自分用の聖書でいろいろな
疑問の答えを見つけられるので—
they were so excited to find answers
from their own Bible.
大喜びされました
I’m so blessed to be here.
参加できて特権です
This has been the best vacation
今までで
最高の家族旅行になりました
that we have had as a family.
The first time I came to Armenia,
1982年に初めてアルメニアを
訪れた時—
it was in 1982.
And I looked for the Witnesses,
証人たちを探したんですけど—
and I hardly found just a few.
数人しか見つかりませんでした
でも 今回キャンペーンで来たら—
But now that I came
for this campaign,
1万1千人もの証人たちに
会うことができました
we have 11,000 Witnesses!
I’m really so happy!
I really want to come back!
とても嬉しかったです！
是非 また来たいです！
It is our hope that Jehovah God
continues to help
エホバ神の助けにより
あらゆる種類の人々が救われて—
all sorts of people to be saved
真理の正確な知識へと
導かれますように
and come
to an accurate knowledge of truth.
While we
enjoy relative freedom
世界の多くの国は比較的自由ですが—
in many countries
around the world,
時に政府が宣教に禁令や制限を
課すことがあります
at times governments
impose bans
or restrictions
on the preaching work.
ステファノス・デムサス兄弟と
妻のレテベルハン姉妹は—
Brother Stephanos Demsas
serves as a special pioneer
in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia,
エチオピアのアディスアベバで
特別開拓者として奉仕しています
along with his wife, Leteberhan.
長年の逆境のもとで
信仰が試されました
Their faith was tested
during many years of adversity.
何が真理を擁護する助けと
なったでしょうか？
What helped them
champion the truth?
話は今のエリトリアから始まります
Their story began
in what is today Eritrea.
I come from a family
of nine children.
わたしは9人きょうだいの一人です
I joined the navy in 1956.
1956年に海軍に入りました
That was during the time
当時エリトリアは
まだエチオピアの一部でした
when Eritrea was part of Ethiopia.
My brother Gebrehiwot
エリトリアのアスマラにいた兄が
わたしに—
asked me to come to Asmara.
来るようにと言いました
He was studying the Bible
with Jehovah’s Witnesses.
兄はエホバの証人から
聖書を学んでいたんです
I was so impressed
with what he shared with me
聞いたことに非常に感動したので—
that for the rest of my vacation,
その休暇中は聖書研究に没頭しました
Bible study became my priority.
その後 軍役を終えー
In time,
I was discharged from the navy
アディスアベバで仕事をしながら
研究を続けー
and started working
in Addis Ababa,
so I was able to continue studying
バプテスマを受けました
the Bible and get baptized.
その頃 レティも
同じような経験をしていたんです
Leti was also doing the same.
In 1960,
I was attending a nursing college.
看護学校に通っていた1960年に—
一人の看護師が 聖書から
とても興味深い話をしてくれました
There, a nurse shared
some interesting thoughts
with me from the Bible.
Ten other student nurses
also showed interest.
他に10人の生徒が関心を持ちました
But the college
threatened us with dismissal
でも エホバの証人は
禁令下にあったので—
学校側はわたしたちを放校すると
脅しました
because there was a ban
on Jehovah’s Witnesses.
When we were shown from the Bible
真のクリスチャンが迫害される理由を
聖書から教えられ—
why true Christians are persecuted,
研究を続ける気持ちが強まりました
we renewed our determination.
そのうち5人がバプテスマを受けました
Eventually,
five of us were baptized.
後にステファノスと出会い
1964年に結婚しました
In time, I met Stephanos,
and we were married in 1964.
Because of the ban,
禁令下だったので
兄弟たちは少人数で集まりました
the brothers were meeting
in small groups.
Our trust was in Jehovah,
and we made the preaching work
エホバを信頼し—
宣教面でも必ず助けてくださるという
確信をもって祈りました
a matter of prayer,
confident that he would help us.
We saw evidence of this
ひそかに行われた
「ものみの塔」誌の生産には—
with the underground production
of The Watchtower.
エホバの助けがはっきり見られました
Our brothers were of modest means,
兄弟たちは貧しかったのですが—
but they used what they had to buy
a hand-operated duplicating machine
何とかして手動の謄写版印刷機を入手し—
which was used in our home.
それを我が家に置きました
After returning
from our secular work,
仕事から帰ると 二人で
「ものみの塔」誌を印刷したものです
Leti and I would get busy
making copies of The Watchtower.
We would play music
so our neighbors
近所の人に印刷機の音が
聞こえないように—
wouldn’t hear the sound
of the duplicator.
音楽を鳴らしながら作業しました
In 1974,
1974年に皇帝ハイレ・セラシエが
退去させられるや否や—
Emperor Haile Selassie was deposed.
This Communist government quickly began
新しい共産主義政府は
恐怖政治を開始し—
a campaign called “Red Terror”
反政府分子の疑いのある者を
容赦なく糾弾しました
against any supposed political opposer.
Now, just having a typewriter
or a duplicating machine
タイプライターや印刷機を
所有しているだけで—
投獄されるか
死刑になりました
could put you in prison
or even have you killed.
反政府思想が印刷されている紙切れを
たまたま拾っただけでも—
Picking up a paper
from the street
with something printed on it
against the government
命を危うくする羽目になりました
could put one’s life in danger.
誰かが突然 行方不明になる
ということもよくありました
It was common
for people to disappear.
Sadly, my youngest brother,
わたしの弟イーヨブも
その犠牲になりました
Eyob, was a victim.
He disappeared on his way home
帰宅途中に行方不明になり—
and was never seen again.
いまだに消息が分かりません
そういう危険な状況で—
With the situation
being very dangerous,
娘のジャネットを無事に育てられるか
とても不安でした
we were quite concerned
raising our daughter, Janet.
でも エホバに全幅の信頼を置いたとき—
But as we fully trusted in Jehovah,
we felt his loving protection.
愛ある保護を実感しました
From time to time,
sections of the city
街の一区画が突然
封鎖されることもありました
were suddenly blockaded.
This happened one morning
as a translator
ある朝 一人の翻訳者が印刷用の原紙を
うちに持ってくる途中で—
was heading to our home
to deliver stencils for printing.
封鎖が始まりました
Urgently, he telephoned
彼は急いで電話をかけてきて—
informing us
that a house-to-house search
一軒一軒 捜索されていると
知らせてきました
was under way.
うちには出版物が山のようにあり—
Our house was full of publications
along with a duplicator
and typewriters!
印刷機もタイプライターもありました
Just after the phone call,
翻訳者からの電話の後すぐ
3人の兵士が捜索に入ってきました
three soldiers
entered our compound to search.
At that moment,
その時 わたしは 彼らを
盲目にしてくださいと祈りました
I prayed silently
that Jehovah would blind them.
Entering the room
where the duplicator
部屋に入ってきた兵士は—
and stacks
of freshly printed literature were,
印刷機と印刷したばかりの
出版物の山を見て—
one soldier asked,
“What is all this?”
“これはどういう代物だ”と
聞いてきました
“Oh, this is a duplicator that we use
“はい この印刷機で—”
“ここにある聖書関係の出版物を
印刷します”
to print these Bible materials.”
Completing his search,
捜索を終え
部屋を出た兵士に—
he went outside
to the commander,
指令官が聞きました
who asked him,
“What did you find?”
“何か見つけたか”
驚いたことに兵士は—
To our utter amazement,
“何もありませんでした”
after seeing everything,
he answered:
“ここでは何も見つからないと
思います”と言ったんです
“Nothing!
We won’t find anything here.”
In the late 1970’s
and into the early 80’s,
1970年代後半から80年代前半にかけて—
another wave
of vicious persecution occurred.
また 別の厳しい迫害が起きました
A number of faithful brothers
were imprisoned,
多くの兄弟たちが投獄され—
tortured, and murdered.
拷問にかけられ 殺されました
I was taken from my work place
because of my neutral stand
中立の立場ゆえに
わたしも職を失い 投獄されました
and put in prison.
When I think about living through
those difficult times,
あの困難な時代を思い返すと—
イザヤ 54章17節にある
エホバの約束は—
I am reminded of Isaiah 54:17
本当に真実だと思います
where Jehovah promised us:
“あなたを攻めるために
形造られる武器は—”
“No weapon formed against you
will have any success.”
“どれも功を奏さない”
Finally, in 1991,
ようやく1991年に—
a liberal government came to power.
自由主義政府になりました
They gave us legal recognition
エホバの証人も法的認可と—
崇拝の自由を手にしました
and freedom of worship.
With these difficult,
dangerous years
危険で困難だった時代が終わり—
now behind us,
we were assigned to the circuit work
わたしたちは
エリトリアとエチオピアでの—
巡回奉仕に割り当てられました
in Eritrea and Ethiopia.
By now, Eritrea was becoming
その後 エリトリアは
独立国家になり—
an independent country,
and this brought about
兄弟たちにとっては 別の試練が始まりました
new challenges for the brothers.
若い兄弟たちが逮捕 投獄されています
Some young brothers
were arrested and imprisoned
because of their Christian stand.
パウロがヘブライ 13章3節に書いたとおりです
Paul wrote at Hebrews 13:3:
“獄につながれている人たちのことを—”
“いつも思いなさい”
“Keep in mind those in prison,
“自分も共につながれているかのように”
as though you were imprisoned with them.”
After enjoying the circuit work
巡回奉仕を15年 楽しんだ後に—
for 15 years,
we faced another change.
また別の変化がありました
We were invited to serve at Bethel
べテルでのフルタイム・コミューター奉仕です
as full-time commuters.
禁令に耐えたり—
What has helped us to endure
through the ban years
いろいろな変化に順応したりするのに
助けになってきたのが—
and to adjust to the many changes
自分たちの霊的習慣です
is our spiritual study program.
We’re in full agreement
エレミヤ 17章7節は
まったくその通りだと思います
with Jeremiah 17:7:
“Blessed is the man
“エホバに依り頼む者は祝福される”
who puts his trust in Jehovah.”
It also brings us much happiness
娘のジャネットが20年間
正規開拓を続けてきたのも—
to know that our daughter, Janet,
has been serving
本当に幸せなことだと思います
as a regular pioneer
for 20 years now.
Each assignment
has had its challenges
割り当てにはそれぞれの
難しさがありましたが—
but many rewards and blessings.
それを上回る祝福がありました
I’m not young anymore;
わたしは 今年で
もう77歳になります
I’m 77 years old.
And I’m 74 years old.
わたしは74歳です
We are now serving
as special pioneers.
今は特別開拓奉仕をしています
When we think about all the changes
that we’ve been through,
これまでの困難を思い返すとき—
“ここにわたしがおります！
わたしを遣わしてください”という—
we realize
that the words at Isaiah 6:8:
イザヤ 6章8節の言葉は—
“Here I am! Send me!”
すべての人に当てはまることが
わかります
are, not just for young people,
but for all of us.
It is very encouraging to see
何が生じようとも
エホバに忠実を保つという—
Stephanos
and Leteberhan’s determination
ステファノスとレテベルハンの
決意に励まされます
to stay faithful to Jehovah,
come what may.
We know that Jehovah
looks with delight
エホバは長年の奉仕を
喜んでおられるに違いありません
on their many years of service.
Some of our brothers in Canada
カナダの兄弟たちも迫害を受けました
underwent similar persecution.
エホバはどのように
助けられたでしょうか？
How did Jehovah help them?
Pay special attention
to the numerous acts of courage
真理を擁護した人たちが示した
数多くの勇気ある行動に注目しましょう
displayed by these
champions of truth.
Preaching in the province of Quebec
was a real challenge.
ケベック州で宣教活動を行なうには—
多くの困難を乗り越え
なければなりませんでした
The Catholic Church
was present
in every sphere of public life.
カトリック教会の影響力が
非常に大きかったからです
In the early ’40s,
the persecution
1940年代前半—
took on quite a bit
迫害はさらに厳しくなり—
of emphasis.
多くの証人たちが逮捕されました
Many Witnesses were being arrested.
Any excuse was used.
逮捕のためにはどんな口実でも
用いられましたが—
Peddling without a license
よくあったのは
“無許可訪問販売”で—
—this was a favorite excuse.
エホバの証人は宗教文書を
所持しているところを見つかると—
Jehovah’s Witnesses were put in prison
whenever they were seen
with religious literature.
必ず投獄されました
It had got so bad in Quebec
ケベックでの状況が非常に
悪化していることを受けて—
that it was decided to circulate a petition,
エホバの証人は カナダ全土で
嘆願書を配布することを決めました
and this petition was circulated
throughout Canada.
And it called
on the government of Quebec
これは 迫害を終わらせるよう
ケベック州政府に求めるもので—
to put an end
to this persecution.
嘆願書に署名した人は
60万人にも上りました
And interestingly,
some 600,000 people
signed the petition.
The Witnesses distributed
証人たちは
「ケベックの燃える憎しみ」と題する—
a very fiery tract
強烈な内容の冊子を出版しました
called the Burning Hate of Quebec.
And in this tract,
この冊子の中で証人たちは—
they showed
what was really happening
警察官の行動や違法な逮捕や
暴徒による襲撃といった—
—the actions of the policemen,
the illegal arrests,
the mob action.
起きている現実を明らかにしました
Within four months,
4か月もたたないうちに
800の新しい訴訟が起こされました
there were 800 new court cases.
最終的に 400人の
エホバの証人に関して—
So here,
for 400 Jehovah’s Witnesses,
you had 1,600 court cases.
1,600の訴訟が
起こされたことになります
The seriousness
その後 証人たちが扇動罪で
訴えられるようになると—
of the court cases increased,
in that now
状況はいっそう厳しくなりました
they were accusing
the brothers of sedition.
もし有罪になれば 10年以上—
If convicted,
it was more than 10
12年ないし15年の懲役刑となる
おそれがあります
—maybe 12 or 15—
years in prison.
We had one brother,
Aimé Boucher,
エメイ・ブーシェという一人の兄弟は
逮捕され 扇動罪で訴えられました
who was arrested
and charged with sedition.
Aimé Boucher
was a very poor brother,
でも 兄弟は ケベックの農村地域で
とても貧しい生活をしている人で—
who lived
in a rural part of Quebec.
And he actually
裁判所に出頭するときは
なんと自分の牛車でやって来ました
went to court
with his ox and buggy.
And on the way to court,
裁判所へ向かう途中
兄弟は伝道して また逮捕されました
he was preaching,
so he was arrested again.
審問の後 有罪判決が言い渡されました
They had the court hearing,
and he was condemned.
He was found guilty of sedition.
理由は扇動罪です
And his case went up
to the Court of Appeal
上訴しましたが—
ケベックの控訴裁判所は
エホバの証人に敵対的だったため—
—and at that time, the Court of Appeal
of Quebec was very hostile—
敗訴しました
and he lost on appeal,
so it went up
to the Supreme Court of Canada.
この件は カナダの
最高裁判所に持ち込まれます
And by this time,
このとき 扇動罪で告発されている
兄弟姉妹がほかに何人かいました
there were several
other brothers and sisters
also charged on sedition,
つまり もしブーシェ兄弟が
敗訴すれば—
which meant that if he lost his case,
その兄弟姉妹たちも
非常に長い懲役刑を—
we had several going to prison
for very lengthy prison terms.
言い渡されるおそれがあった
ということです
When Brother Boucher’s case
ブーシェ兄弟の件は
最高裁判所で審理され—
came before the Supreme Court,
裁判は兄弟に不利な方向で進みました
he lost by a majority of one.
The Catholic judges
all ruled against him,
カトリック信者の裁判官は皆
兄弟に不利な判決を下し—
and they found that the tract
「ケベックの燃える憎しみ」の冊子は
扇動的である としました
the Burning Hate of Quebec
was seditious.
Our lawyers looked at the situation,
弁護士はこれを見て 祈って考えました
prayed about it, and thought:
“どうしたらよいだろう？
負けるわけにはいかない”
‘What can we do?
We can’t lose this battle.’
And they realized that in Canada
そして 気づいたのが めったに
使われていませんでしたが—
there was a very rarely used provision
カナダには最高裁判所に対して—
of asking the Supreme Court
for a rehearing.
再審理を求められる規定がある
ということでした
At the rehearing,
one of the Catholic judges
再審理で
一人のカトリック教徒の裁判官は—
was willing to discuss further
the issue of sedition.
扇動罪の件について
さらに議論しようとしました
And to be guilty of sedition,
しかし 扇動罪とされるのは
暴力に訴えた場合です
you have to incite to violence.
So our attorney asked them:
それで エホバの証人側の
弁護士は言いました
“Please, look at the record.
“どうぞ 記録をご覧になって—”
“Show the court
where Jehovah’s Witnesses
“エホバの証人が暴力に訴えた
証拠を出してください”
incited to violence.”
And finally, they were able
to convince a court they were wrong.
ついに裁判官たちは誤りを認め—
裁判所は一審判決を覆し
ブーシェ兄弟は勝訴しました
And so they overturned
their initial decision,
and Brother Boucher’s case
was victorious.
This dealt with all
the accusations of sedition
政府は この判例をもとに
解決を図ったため—
それまでの扇動罪に関する訴訟は
すべてこの判決に沿って扱われ—
and really brought to an end
the vicious opposition,
because that case
was the one the government
こうして 悪意に満ちた反対を
終わらせることができました
was hoping would work out for them.
There is one case
that’s quite noteworthy in Quebec.
注目に値する
ケベックでの訴訟が一つあります
And it’s a case of the priest
ある司祭が連邦警察を呼び出し—
calling up the federal police
to come and interrupt
エホバの証人の集会を中断させ—
講演者をケベック州から
強制退去させたという事件です
a meeting of Jehovah’s Witnesses
and expel the speaker
from the province of Quebec.
The police obeyed the priest.
司祭の言いなりになった警察は
集会に乗り込み—
They went to the meeting,
they took the brother,
兄弟を連行して
オンタリオまで護送しました
and they escorted him
out of the province into Ontario.
And to disrupt a religious meeting
was a criminal act.
宗教的な集会を中断させるのは
犯罪行為です
For the first time
—and it’s at the level of the Supreme Court—
最高裁は ３人の警察官が
集会を妨害 あるいは中断して—
they found that the three policemen
had to pay moral damages
to the brothers
兄弟たちに人格的損害を与えたとの判断を
初めて下しました
for intercepting,
or interrupting, the meeting.
This has never happened before.
これは前例のないことでした
And when it came up
to the Supreme Court,
最高裁は 全員一致で
ケベック州に不利な判決を下しました
they unanimously ruled
against the province of Quebec.
The section on religious freedom
信教の自由に関して学ぶと
こうした判例が出てきます
is the result of these court cases.
Every lawyer in Canada
(whether in Quebec or in English Canada),
カナダでは ケベックでも
英語圏のカナダでも—
法律を学ぶ弁護士はみな
こうした訴訟を必ず勉強します
when he studies law,
must review these cases.
They are the fundamentals
of religious freedom.
これらの判例は 信教の自由の
基礎となっています
And they represent
the different areas
警察や政府の行動や犯罪行為など—
—police action, government action,
criminal action—
様々な分野で大きな意味がありますし—
and they lay a very nice basis
わたしたちが得ている
自由の土台を据えた判例でもあります
for our freedoms today.
Our purpose is to be able
to preach the good news
わたしたちが目指すのは
良い知らせを伝え—
and to direct people’s attention
toward the Bible.
人々の注意を聖書に向けることです
But our court cases
have helped governments,
しかし こうした訴訟事例は
政府や裁判所や裁判官や当局者たちが—
courts, judges,
宗教の自由に関して
正しい見方を持つ上で—
and officials
to have the right point of view
助けとなっています
on the issue of religious freedom.
The endurance and hard work
of our brothers in Quebec
ケベックの兄弟たちの
忍耐と勤勉な働きは—
truly resulted in a witness
to the nations.
あらゆる国民に対する証しとなりました
While the hope
for a positive outcome
期待や希望があると
力がわきますが—
can at times provide us
with needed motivation,
この体制では 当局の助けを
いつも期待できるわけではありません
we can’t always expect support
from the authorities
in this system of things.
同じことが 生活で直面する
どんな試練についても言えます
The same applies
in many areas of life,
whatever trials we may face.
家族や友人を亡くしたことが
おありかもしれません
Perhaps you have lost
a loved one in death.
すぐそこまで来ている時を
楽しみにするなら—
Looking forward to a time
just around the corner
忍耐しやすくなります
can help us endure.
それが 今月の
ミュージックビデオのテーマです
That’s also the title
of this month’s music video,
“Just Around the Corner
—もうすぐそこに—”
Just Around the Corner.
小鳥の歌声
You can hear the songbirds singing,
And you watch the clouds roll by.
聞こえています
瞳に飛び込む
Then you’re walking in the valley
As the sun shines in a clear blue sky.
青空 光る雲
You’re welcoming your loved ones,
And you can’t believe your eyes.
弾む足音
集う友たち
Yes, this earthly Paradise
Was just around the corner.
始まるパラダイス
そう Just Around the Corner
その丘の上に
There’s a house down in the valley
And a house high on the hill.
家が見えます
There is singing by the river
As the water flows and turns the mill.
湧き出る泉が
しらべを奏でます
黄金に染まる
The golden fields are waiting.
Let the harvesting begin.
豊かな大地
すべて新しい
Once the world we’re living in
Was just around the corner.
そう Just Around the Corner
伝えたい　素晴らしい愛の源を
It’s great to share with friends who care
The things that we looked forward to.
悲しい涙は
Now every tear has disappeared.
The world is young, and life is new.
どこにもないこと
風が届けます
There’s the sound of happy voices
And the scent of new mown hay.
喜びの声
愛する家族の
Now you’re calling to your loved ones
As you start another perfect day.
名前を呼んでいる
あふれる感謝を
Then we thank our God, Jehovah,
For his tender loving care.
わたしの神に
この祝福は
Yes, the blessings we all share
Were just around the corner.
そう Just Around the Corner
昔に夢見た瞬間が 今ついに
And evʹry day I smile and say,
“How good to see your happy face!”
ʹCause once, it seemed, I only dreamed
That you’d be in my warm embrace.
両手であなたを
強く抱きしめる
それはもうすぐ
Waiting ʹround the corner
Is a world I long to see.
始まるのです
優しいエホバの
It’s a promise from Jehovah.
It’s a guaranteed reality.
約束されたこと
その日を待ちわび
And it’s hard to get downhearted
When I think of what’s in store.
心に描く
ほらすぐそこに
It’s the day I’m waiting for,
And it’s just around the corner.
そう Just Around the Corner
What a beautiful song!
とても美しい歌です！
Personally, I lost my father
個人的な話ですが
わたしは2歳の時に父を亡くしました
when I was two years old.
He was a soldier in World War II
and was killed in battle.
第二次世界大戦の兵士で
戦いで亡くなり—
I never had an opportunity
to get to know him.
父を知る機会はありませんでした
Growing up,
I missed having a father
成長するにつれ 自分だけ
父親がいないため寂しく思いました
because I saw
everyone else had one.
So I look forward to observing
the earthly resurrection
それで 地上の復活を観察し
父を見つけるのを楽しみにしています
and seeing my physical father,
and I hope that both he
and my mother
父と母が楽園でエホバを
崇拝することを願っています
will want to worship
Jehovah in Paradise.
Thank you for sharing that,
Brother Lösch.
レッシュ兄弟 話してくださり
ありがとうございます
When my father comes back
in the resurrection,
わたしも父が復活してきたら
両手を広げて歓迎したいです
I look forward to welcoming him
with open arms.
He was a keen student
of history and the Bible,
父は 歴史と聖書を
熱心に学んでいたので—
and so he will want to know
all about what took place
終わりの時に生じたことを
何でも知りたいと思うはずです
during this time of the end.
So my family and I
will have a good time
家族皆で語り合うのを
楽しみにしています
filling him in on what took place.
This music video
and some of the videos we’ve seen
このミュージックビデオや
ここ数年の地区大会のビデオで—
the past few years
at regional conventions
将来の希望をはっきり
思い描くことができました
have painted such a clear picture
of the hope we have for the future.
真理を擁護するために
懸命に努力するなら—
And if we work hard
as champions of the truth,
that hope will become
a reality very soon.
その希望は間もなく現実となります
Well said.
その通りです
And speaking of champions
of the truth,
では 真理を擁護すること
ついてのプログラムを—
we would like
to conclude this program
with greetings from our brothers
and sisters in Romania,
ヨーロッパの南東に位置する国
ルーマニアの兄弟姉妹からの—
あいさつで閉じましょう
a country situated
in the southeast of Europe.
Some of you may know Romania
ルーマニアというと ナイあるいは
パンパイプという伝統楽器を—
for its traditional instrument
called the nai, or pan flute.
思い浮かべる方もいるでしょう
It’s made of wood
and has around 20 pipes,
木製で 20ほどのパイプが
湾曲状に並べられています
arranged in a curved array.
The pitch is adjusted
with beeswax,
蜜ろうをパイプに入れて調律します
which is introduced
in the pipes.
The brothers and sisters
ルーマニア北部のチェルテゼ北会衆の
兄弟姉妹が愛を送っています
in the Certeze North Congregation,
in the north of Romania,
send us their love.
この会衆はウクライナとの
国境近くに位置し—
The congregation is located
near the Ukrainian border,
その地域は 鮮やかな色の
民族衣装で有名です
an area known
for its brightly colored folk costumes.
The congregation
is made up of families
会衆は数世代にわたる
証人家族で構成されており—
with many generations
of Witnesses,
so they have been
champions of truth
長年にわたって真理を擁護しています
for a long time.
The truth reached this area
80年ほど前に この地域に
真理が伝わりました
about 80 years ago,
and now the congregation
is made up of 126 publishers.
今ではこの会衆に
126人の伝道者がいます
They conduct
about 90 Bible studies,
約90件の聖書研究が司会されており
多くの人は集会に出席しています
of which many
attend the meetings.
Because there is
a large concentration
of Witnesses in the area,
the congregation territory
この地域には証人が
特に集中しているため—
is only five kilometers,
会衆の区域は端から端まで
5キロぐらいしかなく—
or a little over three miles,
from the one end to the other.
一つの区域カードには
家が5軒ほどしかありません
Each territory card
has only about five houses.
Because of that,
the congregation
それで 最大200キロ
離れた区域まで行き—
regularly assists
with working territory
up to 200 kilometers,
定期的に奉仕の援助をしています
or about 124 miles away.
The brothers and sisters
チェルテゼ北会衆の兄弟姉妹—
of the Certeze North Congregation
そして世界本部にいるわたしたちも—
send all of you
champions of the truth
真理を擁護している
皆さんを愛しています
their love and greetings
and so do all of us
at world headquarters.
ニューヨーク市ブルックリンから
JW Broadcastingでした
This is JW Broadcasting
in Brooklyn, New York.